<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>CulDeVu</title>
    <link>http://culdevu.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on CulDeVu</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 12 Aug 2018 20:02:01 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://culdevu.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>2018 08 12 Nopelepsy 03</title>
      <link>http://culdevu.github.io/post/2018-08-12-nopelepsy-03/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Aug 2018 20:02:01 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://culdevu.github.io/post/2018-08-12-nopelepsy-03/</guid>
      <description>Hello again! This one is a doozy, but that&#39;s okay. We&#39;ll get through it together
What&#39;s changed For one, Nopelepsy is public on Github now! So that&#39;s cool.
There&#39;s been a big rewrite since last time. Firstly, the Java implementation was ported to C++, and a lot of the single-threaded functionality I figured out how to re-cast into algebraic operations on wide vectors. So that&#39;s cool too. In fact, that&#39;s what most of this is going to be about</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nopelepsy Technical Introduction</title>
      <link>http://culdevu.github.io/post/2018-01-02-nopelepsy-02/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://culdevu.github.io/post/2018-01-02-nopelepsy-02/</guid>
      <description>In my last post a little under two years ago, I talked about a theoretical way to tackle the problem of removing flashes from video, specifically those that can cause epileptic events. Due to technical limitations, time, and scope change, this project has changed a lot over that time. A couple months ago I stopped stalling and buckled down to actually built a working version of the damn thing. It took a lot of trial and error, false starts, and good old fashioned procrastination, but I have a working copy now call Nopelepsy.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tools for Photosensitive Epilepsy I: Flashing</title>
      <link>http://culdevu.github.io/post/2016-03-31-nopelepsy-01/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://culdevu.github.io/post/2016-03-31-nopelepsy-01/</guid>
      <description>In 2009 engineers from the University of Wisconsin released a piece of software called PEAT. This software has been used in medicine since as a tool to diagnose patients with photosensitive epilepsy. This is a disease where strobing lights cause seizures, and it currently has no cure. Things that trigger it include lightning, flashing sirens, flickering lights, and other similar strobe effects. Other triggers that seem unrelated, but are also very cyclic in nature, include rapidly changing images, and even certain stationary stripes and checkerboard patterns.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Microfacet Importance Sampling: For Dummies</title>
      <link>http://culdevu.github.io/post/2016-02-02-microfacet-dummies/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Feb 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://culdevu.github.io/post/2016-02-02-microfacet-dummies/</guid>
      <description>Despite how important of a topic good importance sampling is in the area of global illumination, it&#39;s usually left out of all common-English conversations and tutorials about path tracing (with the exception of the Lambertian case, which is a good introduction to importance sampling). If you want to get into microfacet importance sampling, multiple importance sampling, or even, God forbid, Metropolis light transport, you&#39;re on your own. And, probably for a good reason.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mathematics of Origami: Flat Folding</title>
      <link>http://culdevu.github.io/to_be_organized_later/2015-12-15-flat-folding/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Dec 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://culdevu.github.io/to_be_organized_later/2015-12-15-flat-folding/</guid>
      <description>So. Back at this.
First things first. You can safely disregard most everything I said last post. All of that was very observation-based, and is actually incorrect in almost every way. Which might seem strange, cause most of it made sense. For clarity and completeness, though, here&#39;s a list of why everything last post was wrong:
 The idea that a fold is a collection of fold segments in order starts falling apart after you do certain folds, like petal folds.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Origami and the Associated Maths</title>
      <link>http://culdevu.github.io/to_be_organized_later/2015-11-09-origami-01/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://culdevu.github.io/to_be_organized_later/2015-11-09-origami-01/</guid>
      <description>So this is going to be another one of those write-it-out-so-that-I-can-better-understand-it sort of things. Just a heads up. This IS a journal, after all, and functions as advertisement second.
So. Origami and mathematics. We know that the two are related because, if you fold a piece of paper the same way twice, you&amp;rsquo;ll get two of the same shape, so there&amp;rsquo;s rules governing it. And some smart people have tried figuring out those rules.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fluid dynamics update</title>
      <link>http://culdevu.github.io/to_be_organized_later/2015-09-29-fluid-dyanamic-update/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Sep 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://culdevu.github.io/to_be_organized_later/2015-09-29-fluid-dyanamic-update/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m not really going to talk about much math-y stuff this time. I&amp;rsquo;ve covered too much ground since my last entry to be able to remember all the pitfalls I ran into. So this time I&amp;rsquo;m only really going to be talking about the general algorithm, how I deal with the pitfalls of the marker particle method, and the ongoing translation to CUDA. And probably share some of my Mario Maker levels.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Factored BRDF Representation</title>
      <link>http://culdevu.github.io/to_be_organized_later/2015-07-20-factored-brdf/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://culdevu.github.io/to_be_organized_later/2015-07-20-factored-brdf/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s been quite a while.
So I&amp;rsquo;ve been working on life/jobs/family/etc the past couple months. A couple weeks ago, however, I decided to implement a type of arbitrary BRDF sampling based on factoring large matrices, found here: http://gfx.cs.princeton.edu/proj/brdf/brdf.pdf
The idea is to convert the BRDF into a series of matrix representations in such a way that
\[ f_r(\omega_i, \omega_o)(wi \cdot \textbf{n}) \approx \sum{l=1}^{L}{ F_l(\omega_o) u_l(\theta_h) v_l(\phi_h) } \]
, where \( F_l \), \( u_l \), and \( vl \) are massive matrices that depend on outgoing direction, half angle azimuth, and half angle zenith about surface normal, respectively.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Planetary Biomes</title>
      <link>http://culdevu.github.io/to_be_organized_later/2015-04-25-planetary-biomes/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 25 Apr 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://culdevu.github.io/to_be_organized_later/2015-04-25-planetary-biomes/</guid>
      <description>Not many images or videos this time around, unfortunately. It&amp;rsquo;s mostly about updates about what I&amp;rsquo;m up to and what I&amp;rsquo;m working on.
So, first off, the non-euclidean stretchy game thingy. Turns out that some people in my art class had taken an interest in it when I was working on it in class, and they offered to help offload some of the content generation, like making art, animations, level design, etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>HBR: Human Based Rendering</title>
      <link>http://culdevu.github.io/to_be_organized_later/2015-01-31-hbr/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Jan 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://culdevu.github.io/to_be_organized_later/2015-01-31-hbr/</guid>
      <description>Heyy all!
So the graphics professor at school here was talking to me and he was like &amp;ldquo;you know what would be a cool idea?&amp;rdquo; Turns out, it WAS a cool idea.
So! I present to you:
HBR: Human Based Rendering (the photon mapping of the next generation) The general idea is to either get the user that&amp;rsquo;s looking at a screen to plot the photons themselves, or somehow crowd-source rendering an environment by manually tracing out light paths.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Portfolio</title>
      <link>http://culdevu.github.io/portfolio/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://culdevu.github.io/portfolio/</guid>
      <description>I have tried my best to tinker with a lot of different things in a lot of different areas, from CUDA programming, to game programming; from computer graphics to computational physics. I really like to spend a couple months really digging down into a particular topic, trying to delve as deep as I can into any given topic as I can before something else steals my curiosity. Because of this, they end up being kinda complex, and detailed enough for me to be able to spend multiple months working on.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Resume</title>
      <link>http://culdevu.github.io/resume/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://culdevu.github.io/resume/</guid>
      <description>As stated in the sidebar, I&amp;rsquo;m currently job-seeking. My resume can be found as a pdf here and also embeded using your browser&amp;rsquo;s default pdf viewer below:</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>